<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<topic>
<default>
SIPB is MIT's volunteer student computing group, improving computing at MIT since 1969. Today, SIPB projects provide innovative services and special expertise to the MIT community. Their office is just outside the Athena cluster in the student center W20, and you are welcome to come by to ask SIPB for help or to hang around, use the computers, and maybe get involved.
</default>
<answer question="acronym">
Student Information Processing Board
</answer>

<answer question="services">
scripts.mit.edu: Get your own blog or wiki, or run any web app! 
                 The SIPB scripts server runs CGI scripts out 
		   of your Athena locker.

xvm.mit.edu: Your own virtual server. Reliable, easy, and flexible.

debathena.mit.edu: Bringing MIT's Athena environment to Debian 
                   and Ubuntu, first for our laptops, and then 
                   back to the clusters.

linerva.mit.edu: Remote login access to Athena on a powerful 
                 Debian GNU/Linux server running Debathena.

Documentation: Helpful and informative documents about various 
               computing topics at MIT, written by SIPB.

Computer Help: Have a computing question or need some help? 
               Come drop by our office.
</answer>

<answer question="events">

IAP classes:     Teach or learn. Knowledge is power. 
                 http://sipb.mit.edu/iap/

SIPB Cluedumps:  Every year, SIPB hosts a number of computer-related 
                 technical talks on a variety of subjects.

Hackathons:      Like coding? Come work on cool projects with us 
		   at SIPB! We're always looking for new members, 
                 so feel free to drop by our Hackathons to help us 
                 improve computing at MIT.

SIPB Computer Tours:   At the beginning of each year, SIPB offers 
                       tours of the MIT computing infrastructure, including 
                       Athena server rooms, interesting labs.
SIPB Computer Stories: Come listen to interesting computer stories 
                       about MIT in this annual event.

</answer>

<answer question="contact">

The SIPB office is W20-557 in the Student Center at 84 Mass Ave. You can call 617/253-7788 (x3-7788) or e-mail sipb@mit.edu with questions.
</answer>


</topic>
